A Guide to the Ford Foundation records, Asset Based Community Development, Community and Resource Development, Office Files of Frances Korten FA250
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation records, Asset Based Community Development, Community and Resource Development, Office Files of Frances Korten
1990-1996
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation
Geithner, Peter F.
Korten, Frances F.
FA250
.8 Cubic Feet 2 letter document containers
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research with select materials restricted as noted. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC.
Scope and Contents
The collection primarily consists of report drafts with memos and published articles related to the Ford Foundation's efforts to establish community forestry practices in Asia.
Biographical / Historical
Frances F. Korten worked as a Ford Foundation program officer for 20 years, from 1977-1996, in Southeast Asia and New York. In the 1970s and '80s, Korten was a program officer in the Jakarta, Indonesia and Manila, Philippines field offices. In the 1990s, she worked in New York as a program officer in the Rural Poverty and Resources and Community and Resource Development units.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into one series: Asia - Community Forestry Review - Material sent to Frances Korten by Peter Geithner
Biographical / Historical
Between 1976 and 1993, the Ford Foundation invested more than $30 million in support of community forestry programs under the Rural Poverty and Resources Program. Two major goals of the program were to 1.) reduce poverty among people living in rural areas and 2.) improve the management of natural resources. This work required building relationships with nongovernmental organizations (NGOs) as well as government forest departments with jurisdiction over public lands. The program aimed to give people who rely on forests for their livelihood to have a voice in how forests are managed. In the 1980s and 1990s, the Ford Foundation established community forestry programs in the Philippines, India, Thailand, Indonesia, China, and Bangladesh.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
This material was transferred to RAC in 2019 by the Ford Foundation and ingested by RAC as Accession 2019:107.
- Asia - Community Forestry Review - Material sent to Frances Korten by Peter Geithner, 1
  - Social Forestry Review Report - Figures/Diagrams and Field Responses Correspondence, 1994 May-July (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - The Ford Foundation Bulletin, New Delhi Office - Autumn 1995 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Scope and Contents
    Includes:
    People and Forests
    Case Study
    Who benefits? A Dialogue on Gender Equity and JFM
    Reaching Out to Rural Communities
    Reflections on the Road to Beijing
    Shakti Shalini - A Helping Hand
  - Joint Management of Forest Lands, Experiences from South Asia, A Ford Foundation Program Statement, Mark Poffenberger, 1990 January (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Forest Management Partnerships: Regenerating India's Forests, Executive Summary of the Workshop on Sustainable Forestry, New Delhi, 1990 September 10-12 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Drafts of Forestry Reports and Correspondence, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Community Forestry: A New Paradigm and Practice, Review of the Ford Foundation's Programs in Community Forestry in Asia, Eva Wollenberg and Mary Hobley - Monograph Draft, 1994 May 23 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Forestry for Sustainable Rural Development: A Review of Ford Foundation-Supported Community Forestry Programs in Asia - Drafts, 1995 November-1996 January (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Experiences and Advances in the Development of Community Forestry Programming: A Review of Ford Foundation Supported Community Forestry Programs in Asia, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Community Forestry: A New Paradigm and Practice, Review of the Ford Foundation's Programs in Community Forestry in Asia, Eva Wollenberg and Mary Hobley, Monograph Draft, 1994 May 19 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Review of the Ford Foundation's Programs in Community Forestry in Asia, Eva Wollenberg and Mary Hobley, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 10-12)